Guide to the Lafayette Manuscripts 1792-1834
University of Chicago Library
Lafayette Manuscripts
1792-1834
Codex Ms 303
0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Contains documents, primarily correspondence written by or to Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Montier, Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834). Also included are letters related to Lafayette's son, George Washington du Motier de Lafayette (1779-1849) and grandson, Edmond du Motier de Lafayette (1818-1888). Codex Ms 303.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Digital Images
Original documents, texts, and images represented by digital images linked to this finding aid are subject to U. S. copyright law. It is the user's sole responsibility to secure any necessary copyright permission to reproduce or publish documents, texts, and images from any holders of rights in the original materials.
The University of Chicago Library, in its capacity as owner of the physical property represented by the digital images linked to this finding aid, encourages the use of these materials for educational and scholarly purposes. Any reproduction or publication from these digital images requires that the following credit line be included: Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library.
The images presented here may include materials reflecting the attitudes, language, and stereotypes of an earlier time period. These materials are presented as historical resources in support of study and research. Inclusion of such materials does not constitute an endorsement of their content by the University of Chicago.
The University of Chicago Library appreciates hearing from anyone who may have information about any of the images in this collection.
Scope Note
The Lafayette Manuscripts (Codex Ms 303) comprise primarily documents written by or to Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Montier, Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834). Also included are letters related to Lafayette's son, George Washington du Motier de Lafayette (1779-1849) and grandson, Edmond du Motier de Lafayette (1818-1888).
Many of the earlier letters in the collection bear witness to Lafayette's fortunes and activities during the revolutionary period in France. Though placed in command of an army that was to attack the Austrian Netherlands in 1792, he was declared a traitor to the Legislative Assembly, and captured while trying to flee the country in August 1792. He was held in Prussian and Austrian prisons until 1797. A letter sent to Lafayette by General Alexis Paul Michel le Veneur (August 11, 1792) documents his military activities, while a fragmentary letter from an American correspondent to an unidentified newspaper on May 26, 1796 protests the conditions of his imprisonment.
Letters dating from 1800 to 1812 document Lafayette's retirement to his country estate during the Napoleonic era.
Soon after the Bourbon Restoration, Lafayette became a deputy, speaking and voting consistently on the liberal side. He took an active interest in revolutionary activities abroad, particularly in South America, Poland, Naples, Spain, Greece and Belgium. The largest group of letters in the collection document Lafayette's political activities and private life during this period. Of particular note is an 1825 letter from Lafayette to inventor and artist Samuel F. B. Morse expressing condolences upon the death of Morse's wife.
The final letters in the collection are related to Lafayette's son and grandson, and primarily document private and family affairs.
Following the main portion of the collection are nine files that were formerly part of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Lafayette: a guide to the letters, documents, and manuscripts in the United States / edited by Louis Gottschalk, Phyllis S. Pestieau, Linda J. Pike.
Bonaventure-Lafayette Collection (Ms 304)
Lafayette-Crawford Correspondence (Ms 916)
Subject Headings
Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834;; Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849; Lafayette, Edmond de; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799
INVENTORY
- Notarized letter concerning the Marquis de Lafayette's estate, 1754 June 5. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Autograph letter signed: Le Veneur, Alexis-Paul-Michel, comte Tanneguy, 1746-1833, [Mouron?], France, to General Lafayette, n.p., 1792 Aug. 11. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Autograph letter: Masclet, Joseph, 1760-1833, n.p., to unknown editor, n.p., 1796 May 26. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Chavaniac, France, to Citoyen du Verdier, Paris, 1800 Sept. 6. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to unknown person, n.p., 1808 July 3. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Pelet [de la Lozère], Paris, 1809 June 11. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to unknown person, n.p., 1812 Apr. 28. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Autograph letters signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Antoine Simon Durrieu, n.p., 1819 Aug. 5 and 1820 Sept. 3. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to unknown person, n.p., 1820 Jan. 13. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to unknown person, n.p., 1822 Aug. 8. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Alexandre [Romeuf], n.p., [1823?] May 5. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to Samuel F. B. Morse, 1825, Feb. 11. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to [Alexandre] Chevallon, Paris, 1826 June 10. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to Charles d'Outrepont, Paris, 1826 Feb. 21. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to [Brice?], n.p., 1826 July 6. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to unknown person, n.p., 1826 July 24. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to Francis Allyn, n.p., [1826 Feb.]. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to [Marc-Antoine Jullien de Paris?], n.p., 1826 Oct. 15. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Godin, Chatillon-sur-Seine, France, 1826 Oct. 24. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Autograph letters: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris and La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Antoine Simon Durrieu, n.p., 1828 July 30 and Aug. 8. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Francis Allyn, n.p., 1828 Nov. 9. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letters signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to [Alexandre] Chevallon, Paris, 1829 Apr. 12 and May 19. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to Mary Taylor, Paris, 1829 June 17. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, [Paris?], to [Dominique Vivant] Denon, Paris, [1825?] May 8. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to [Sebastien de] Calvo, n.p., 1830 Oct. 11. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to [Marie-Charlotte-Henriette Roberjot Lallemand], Paris, [1830 Oct. 29]. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to François-Horace-Bastien Sebastiani, Paris, 1830 Dec. 9. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to [Alexandre Roubier] d'Hérambault, Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1831 Feb. 25. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, n.p., to Agricole Lapierre-Châteauneuf, Paris, [1831?]. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Autograph letter signed: Barrot, Théodore Adolphe, 1803-1870, Kingston, Jamaica, to the Marquis de Lafayette, n.p., 1834 Mar.14. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849, Washington, D.C., to Captain Allyn, New York, 1825 Feb. 17. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letters: Levasseur, Auguste, to George Washington Lafayette, 1826 Jan.-Sept. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849, Paris, to Mr. Dutrone, Paris, 1826 Jan. 6. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1779-1849, n.p., to [John Stuart] Skinner, [Baltimore?], [circa 1826]. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Autograph letter signed: Lapierre-Châteauneuf, Agricole, n.p., to George Washington Lafayette, Paris, 1837 Sept. 14. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Edmond de, Paris, to unknown person, n.p., 1852 Nov. 27. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Autograph letter signed: Lafayette, Edmond de, Paris, to unknown person, n.p., 1852 Nov. 20. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Mémoires et documents: correspondance politique, 1780-1786, Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, photostat copies. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, [Paris], to Monsieur le Comte de Mirabeau, [Paris], 1789 Aug. 19. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Manuscript copy of Letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Metz, France, to Marie Charles César Fay, Comte de Latour-Maubourg, 1792 Jan. 22. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Manuscript copy of Letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Metz, France, to Louis de Narbonne, 1792 Jan. 23 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Autograph letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, to [Camilla?] Wright, [ca. 1824] (Photocopy. Tipped into: Mémoires sur la vie et le siècle de Salvatore Rosa / Lady Morgan, call # alc ND623.R8M82 Rare ) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Autograph letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to General Guillaume Pepe, London, 1827 Aug. 18. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, La Grange, Seine-et-Marne, France, to Monsieur Pascault, Paris, 1828 Jan. 2. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Autograph letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to Christopher Hughes, Paris, 1830 June 7. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Letter: Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834, Paris, to [Peter Stephen Duponceau, Philadelphia], 1831 Mar. 14. (Box 2, Folder 9)